<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-sarikaya-hiaps-hostid-prefix-sharing-protocol-00.txt" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Hiaps Protocol ">UDP based Address Registration Protocol for Host Identification and Prefix Sharing</title>




    <author fullname="Behcet Sarikaya" initials="B.S." surname="Sarikaya">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>5340 Legacy Dr. Building 3,</street>

	  <city>Plano</city>

	  <region>TX</region>

	  <code>75024</code>

	  <country>USA</country>
	</postal>

	<email>behcet.sarikaya@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>



    <author fullname="Dirk von Hugo" initials="D.H." surname="von Hugo">
      <organization abbrev="Telekom Innovation Laboratories">Telekom
	Innovation Laboratories</organization>

      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>Deutsche-Telekom-Allee 7</street>

	  <city>D-64295 Darmstadt</city>

	  <code></code>

	  <country>Germany</country>
	</postal>

	<phone></phone>

	<email>Dirk.von-Hugo@telekom.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>







    <author fullname="Marco Spini" initials="M.S." surname="Spini">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street></street>

	  <city>Paris</city>

	  <region></region>

	  <code></code>

	  <country>France</country>
	</postal>

	<email>M.Spini@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2014" />

    <abstract>
      <t>
	IPv6 prefix sharing in policy for convergence applications makes it impossible to track individual quality of service requirements for each host by the policy server. In many other cases, IPv4/IPv6 address sharing makes it impossible to identify a host among those sharing the same IP address. In order to enable it, we define a UDP-based protocol which is based on the sender (host, residential gateway, NAT device, etc.) sending some parameters such as IP addresses of each host  to the receiver (external server, edge router, Web server, etc.).  The protocol enables the external server to identify the host and to do other things like to enforce the quality of service which is specific to the host on its traffic  both uplink and downlink.  </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>
	A number of use cases have been documented that exhibit the issue of uniquely identifying a host among many hosts sharing the same IP address <xref target="I-D.boucadair-intarea-host-identifier-scenarios"/>. However, all these use cases involve IPv4, Network Address Translation (NAT) <xref target="RFC2663"/> and/or tunneling.
	When more than one host share the same address, it becomes impossible to blacklist a misbehaving host without impacting the other hosts or as in the case discussed next, it becomes impossible to enforce a per-subscriber/per-UE policy such as quality of service provisioning and enforcement.
      </t>
      <t>
	An IPv6 related use case belongs to Policy for Convergence (P4C) area in Fixed Mobile Convergence (FMC). The problem occurs when more than one host are assigned IPv6 addresses by local device, e.g. Residential Gateway (RG), sharing the same IPv6 prefix without interaction with the Edge router where the Policy and Charging Control  (PCC) interface is terminated. In such a case, the Policy and Charging Enforcement  function (PCEF) can not apply host specific quality of service for each host.
      </t>


      <t>
	As part of Fixed Mobile Convergence (FMC) standardization, convergence or Policy for Convergence (P4C) is being actively pursued. P4C deals with applying the mobile network such as 3GPP Policy and Charging Control (PCC) to the hosts in a fixed IP network, including the User Equipment (UE) accessing the fixed IP network from home or from a Wi-Fi hot spot <xref target="TS23.203"/>, <xref target="TR23.896"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
	There are several solution proposals for host identification problem <xref target="RFC6967"/>. In <xref target="I-D.williams-exp-tcp-host-id-opt"/>, defines a TCP option to carry the host identifiers, e.g. IPv4 addresses. In this document we define a UDP-based Address registration protocol for host identification problem.

      </t>
      <t>

      </t>
      <t>

      </t>

      <t>


      </t>











      <t>


      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions and Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
	document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
							  target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="oper" title="Policy for Convergence Architecture">
      <t>

      </t>

      <t>
	When a host, e.g. Local_Host_1 in <xref target="arch4"/> attaches to a routed Residential Gateway, RG uses DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation as Requesting Router (RR) to request a prefix, possibly of size /60 for home network. The edge router acts as the Delegating Router (DR). So the edge router assigns the IPv6 prefix to the RG.
	Note that the host can be both 3GPP UE and Fixed device, e.g. PC, IPTV STB,etc.
      </t>

      <t>
	The edge router next initiates an  IP Connectivity Access Network (IP-CAN) session with the policy server, a.k.a. Policy and Charging Rules Function (PCRF) to receive the Quality of Service (QoS) parameters. Edge router provides IPv6 Prefix and User Equipment (UE) ID which in this case is equal to the home network line ID.  IP-CAN session establishment completes with the policy server sending IP CAN Session Establishment Ack to RG.

      </t>
      <t>
	Edge Router binds the IP Subscriber Session for RG with  the IP-CAN session identified by RG ID,  IPv6 Prefix. Edge Router applies admission control and quality of service policy based on the parameters received from the policy server during the IP-CAN session establishment.
      </t>
      <t>
	3GPP UE has to be authenticated. In this case EAP-AKA authentication method is used. RG is the authenticator and AAA server is in 3GPP network.
	At the end of a successful authentication, UE receives its host id, i.e. Network Access Identifier (NAI) in User-Name attribute. Host id contains International Mobile Subscriber Identity (IMSI) and is in Root NAI format defined in <xref target="TS23.003"/>. Root NAI takes the form of "0IMSI@nai.epc.mncMNC.mccMCC.3gppnetwork.org" for EAP AKA authentication, i.e. if the IMSI is 234150999999999 ( mobile country code MCC = 234, mobile network code MNC = 15), the root NAI then takes the form as 0234150999999999@nai.epc.mnc015.mcc234.3gppnetwork.org for EAP AKA authentication.
      </t>

      <t>
	In case of stateless address auto configuration, the host sends a Router Solicitation message to RG and RG sends a Router Advertisement with an IPv6 prefix, the home network prefix. The host creates an 128-bit IPv6 address using this prefix and adding its interface id.  Having completed the address configuration, the host can start communication with the Internet to use the Internet services.

      </t>

      <t>
	Another host, e.g. non-3GPP Visiting Host 1 attaches to RG and also establishes an IPv6 address using the home network prefix. Edge router is not involved with this and all other such address assignments. In this case no authentication is performed. So the host does not receive a host id from 3GPP network.

      </t>
      <t>
	The above operation steps assumed that stateless address auto configuration (SLAAC) is used. DHCPv6 based stateful address assignment can also be used. In case of routed RG, RG can be DHCPv6 relay agent communicating with a DHCPv6 server in the operator's IP network. DHCPv6 server in assigning IPv6 addresses to the hosts uses a method where  /64 prefixes are never shared between hosts in different home networks.
      </t>

      <figure anchor="arch4"
	      title="Policy for Convergence Architecture">
	<artwork><![CDATA[
+-------------+        +-------------+
+---------------+                         |Policy Server|        |  AAA Server |
|Visiting Host 1|--+        Mobile Network+-------------+        +-------------+
+---------------+  |        ---------------------|--------------------------
+----+                          |
+-------------+  |Rout|    +-------------+       |            +-------------+
|Local_Host_1 |--| ed |----| Edge Router |-------+            |  AAA Server/|
+-------------+  | RG |    +-------------+                    |    Proxy    |
+----+                   \                   +-------------+
+---------------+  |                       \
|Visiting Host 2|--+        Fixed IP Network \                   --+-
+---------------+                             \                /      \
\              |Internet|
------------- | Service|
\      /
----
]]></artwork>
      </figure>





      <t>
	The RG does not signal to the edge router the IP6 address assigned to a host, e.g. visiting host 1 or 2, so the edge router acting as Policy and Charging Enforcement Function (PCEF) is not able to start an 3GPP IP-CAN session for  the given host ID, IPv6 Address corresponding to each single host, i.e. the Local_Host_1 and visiting host 1 or 2.

      </t>


      <t>
	Each host in the home network creates an IPv6 address which is global and this address can be used to identify the hosts traffic and would enable PCEF to enforce the proper QoS after establishing an IP-CAN session to download the required parameters. UE id given to the mobile network in <xref target="oper"/> is the home network line id which is the same for all the hosts in the home network.

      </t>

    </section>
    <section anchor="operO" title="Policy for Convergence Solution Overview">
      <t>

      </t>
      <t>
	In the first phase of the solution, for a 3GPP UE, RG sends IPv6 address of the host and the host id as received from 3GPP network during authentication in Address Registration Request message to the edge router. For hosts not authenticated by 3GPP line id can be sent. The timing of this message could be:

      </t>

      <t>
	After SLAAC is completed, e.g. after sending neighbor solicitation message with Target Address is set to the address being checked, in this case the Target Address is the address that RG sends,

      </t>

      <t>
	After DHCPv6 address configuration is completed, in this case IPv6 address in IA Address option (OPTION_IAADDR) is the address that RG sends

      </t>

      <t>
	After receiving the first unicast packet from the host, in this case the source address of the packet is the address that RG sends.

      </t>

      <t>
	RG receives an Address Registration Reply  message and checks the code. If the value is zero then the request has succeeded.

      </t>
      <t>
	After the address registration at the edge router, the edge router goes ahead and communicates with the policy server and gets the quality of service parameters for each host separately. for this purpose the edge router establishes an IP-CAN sub-session as part of the main session RG has established with the policy server separately for each host <xref target="TR23.896"/>.

      </t>
      <t>
	For 3GPP UE, during IP-CAN sub-session establishment, the edge router includes  the International mobile subscriber identity (IMSI) as part of the host id. The edge router also sends IPv6 address as the new parameter.

      </t>
      <t>
	In case of non-3GPP hosts, during IP-CAN sub-session establishment, the edge router includes RG-ID or line id and IPv6 address as new parameters. It also includes IPv6 prefix.
      </t>
      <t>
	The policy server obtains the subscriber's profile related to the host.
	The policy server sends the default QoS of the subscriber and some other information to the edge router.

      </t>
      <t>
	IP-CAN sub-session is established between the edge router and the policy server. Over this session, the policy server gets informed about the quality of service related events. The session remains open until the session is removed as requested by the edge router.

      </t>
      <t>
	The edge router repeats the above procedures for each host that shared the address.

      </t>








    </section>

    <section anchor="reqs" title="HOST_ID Solution">
      <t>
	First the address registration message exchange is used  to register the addresses of the hosts sharing the address/prefix. The receiver (edge router, call server, Web, FTP server) action (determining the location for each such host for emergency calls, applying per-host quality of service, etc.) follows subsequently.

      </t>
      <t>
	Receiver action could be the edge router gets QoS parameters for each host. Edge router enforces the QoS for each host in the active traffic. The call server queries the location server to determine the location of each host.

      </t>
      <t>


      </t>

      <t>
	The call flow of the protocol is shown in <xref target="arch5"/>.

      </t>

      <figure anchor="arch5"
	      title="Call flow">
	<artwork><![CDATA[
Sender (Host, RG, CGN)              Receiver              Policy server
Addr. Conf'ed   |                         |                           |
or other trigger|---Address Reg. Req----->|                           |
					 |<---Address Reg. Reply---|                           |
						      |                         |-- Possible Interactions ->|
					   |                         |    Regarding policy (QoS) |
					   |                         |<- or determining location |
|                         |                           |
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>


      </t>
      <section anchor="nat64" title="NAT64 Host Identification">
	<t>
	  Stateful NAT64 is an IPv4 to IPv6 transition protocol which enables IPv6 hosts to communicate with IPv4-only servers <xref target="RFC6146"/>. In NAT64, the host sends its IPv6 packets to the server which are intercepted by NAT translator which translates IPv6 packets into IPv4 packets before sending them to IPv4 server. In this process the server does not see IPv6 address of the host but instead IPv4 address of NAT64 translator. Therefore NAT64 suffers from the host identification problem in case more than one host is communicating with the server using the same NAT64 translator.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Address registration protocol can be used to enable the server to uniquely identify each host communicating with NAT64. We consider two scenarios which are discussed next.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Address registration protocol can be initiated by the host. NAT64 translator will translate the request and reply messages into IPv4 so that the server can correctly receive the payload. This does not cause a problem because the address and any other parameters will be received unchanged. The server can correctly identify each host using the address parameter.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Address registration protocol can be initiated by NAT64 translator. NAT64 translator can send Address Registration Request message in IPv4 to IPv4-only server. NAT64 translator MUST send IPv6 address of the host in the address parameter. Using  this the server can correctly identify each host.
	</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="messagedefs" title="Address Registration Request/Response Message Definitions">
      <t>
	These messages are sent with UDP header and contain the parameters defined in this section. All parameters are TLV formatted. Length field in UDP header contains the length of the entire datagram.

      </t>
      <section anchor="messagedefadr"
	       title="Address Registration Request Message Definition">

	<t>
	  Address registration request message is sent by the sender (RG, NAT, CGN, Proxy, etc.). It contains  IPv6 address or IPv4 address. The address field can be replicated to register more than one addresses. The sender MUST put a different sequence number into each new address request message it sends to the edge router. Additional data may be sent in this message. for this purpose we define Additional Info TLV.

	</t>

	<figure anchor="routepoption3" title="Address Registration Request ">
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length     |         Sequence #            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Parameters                             |
.                        in TLV format                          .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>Fields:</t>
	<t></t>
	<t>Type:           TBD.</t>
	<t></t>
	<t>Length:          The length of the option. The value is 8 or 20.

	  octets.</t>
	<t>Sequence Number: This field is used by the access router to process the requests from the sender in the sending order.</t>
	<t>Followed by parameters</t>

	<figure anchor="routepoption1" title="Address Parameter ">
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-
|     Type      |    Length     |  Address ...
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-
]]></artwork>
	</figure>


	<t>Fields:</t>
	<t></t>
	<t>Type:           TBD.</t>
	<t></t>
	<t>Length:          The length of the option. The value is 6 or 18.

	  octets.</t>
	<t>
	  Address: IPv4 or IPv6 address.

	</t>

	<figure anchor="routepoption2" title="Additional Info">
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-
|     Type      |    Length     |Additional Info...
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>Fields:</t>
	<t></t>
	<t>Type:           TBD.</t>
	<t></t>
	<t>Length:          The length of the option. The value > 3.

	  octets.</t>
	<t>
	  Additional Info: Parameter such as Host id in Root NAI format, line ID, etc.
	</t>

      </section>


      <section anchor="messagedefadrreply" title="Address Registration Reply Message Definition">

	<t>
	  Address Registration Reply messages are sent by the receiver (Edge Router, Call Server, Web, FTP server, etc.). The receiver MUST set the sequence number field to the value in the request message. The code is set according to the success status of the address request message.

	</t>

	<figure anchor="routep" title="Address Registration Reply">
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length     |         Sequence #            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
+                              Code                             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                            Parameters                         |
.                                                               .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>Fields:</t>
	<t></t>
	<t>Type:           TBD.</t>
	<t></t>
	<t>Length:          The length of the option. The value is 8 or 12, or 24.

	  octets.</t>
	<t>Sequence Number: The value in the reply MUST match the value in the corresponding request.</t>
	<t>Code:  A value indicating the result of the Address
	  Request. A value of zero (0) indicates successful operation. Any other value indicates an unsuccessful operation.</t>
	<t>Parameters: IPv4 or IPv6 address and Host Id. Optional field.</t>
	<t>


	</t>
      </section>

      <t>


      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="dtls" title="Securing Address Registration Protocol for Host Identification">

      <t>
	When address registration protocol is used between the residential gateway and the edge router, there is no need for additional security mechanisms. This is because RG to edge router communication happens over a secured (IPSEC or other mechanisms) tunnel.
	Also the trigger needs to be different than address configuration by the host.
      </t>
      <t>
	When address registration protocol is used between the residential gateway, NAT or CGN and a generic server such as a call server, web server, FTP server, the sender needs to get the receiver's address in order to start the address registration protocol interactions. One such trigger could be the establishment of a session with an external host by a host. This could be session establishment using protocols like TCP, SCTP, etc.
      </t>
      <t>
	When address registration protocol is used between the residential gateway, NAT or CGN and a generic server such as a call server, web server, FTP server, the protocol MUST be secured.  Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) protocol can be used to secure it. DTLS version 1.2 is defined in <xref target="RFC6347"/>. DTLS is Transport Layer Security (TLS) version 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"/> over datagram transport.


      </t>
      <t>

      </t>
      <t>
	DTLS handshake protocol starts with a stateless cookie exchange in which the client, Residential Gateway sends ClientHello message and the server replies with HelloVerifyRequest message which contains a cookie. The client sends ClientHello this time with the cookie. This phase allows the server to verify that Cookie is valid and that the client can receive packets at the
	given IP address. Note that this phase has been added to DTLS and does not exists in TLS.

      </t>

      <t>
	DTLS handshake protocol  continues with essentially the same TLS exchanges such as ServerHello, Certificate, ServerKeyExchange, CertificateRequest and ServerHelloDone messages by the server and Certificate, ClientKeyExchange, CertificateVerify and (Client) Finished messages. With these messages, the client and server exchanges signed certificates, authenticate each other and select a cipher suite to be used to secure the communication between the two. The server replies with ChangeCipherSpec to notify the client that subsequent records will be
	protected under the newly negotiated CipherSpec and keys and (Server) finished message which terminates the full handshake.

      </t>
      <t>
	DTLS session-resuming handshake which is executed after the keys expire is much simpler. The client sends Client Hello to which the server replies with ServerHello, ChangeCipherSpec and Finished message. The client sends ChangeCipherSpec and Finished message to complete the handshake.
      </t>
      <t>

      </t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations ">
      <t>
	IANA is requested to assign a port number for the protocol described in this document.
      </t>
      <t>Two type values are needed to be assigned, one for the address request and another for the reply message.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
	Any security considerations are TBD.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
	TBD.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>



      <reference anchor="TR177">
	<front>
	  <title>Broadband Forum Technical report TR-177, IPv6 in the context of TR-101 Issue 1</title>

	  <author>
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>

	  <date month="November" year="2010" />
	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS23.003">
	<front>
	  <title>3GPP TS23.003, Technical Specification Group Core Network and Terminals;
	    Numbering, addressing and identification
	  </title>

	  <author>
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>

	  <date month="March" year="2013" />
	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS23.203">
	<front>
	  <title>3GPP TS23.203, Policy and Charging Control
	    Architecture</title>

	  <author>
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>

	  <date month="March" year="2013" />
	</front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="TR23.896">
	<front>
	  <title>3GPP TR23.896, Technical Report on Support for fixed broadband access network convergence</title>

	  <author>
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>

	  <date month="February" year="2013" />
	</front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2663"?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3633' ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6146"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6967"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">


      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.boucadair-intarea-host-identifier-scenarios'?>


      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.williams-exp-tcp-host-id-opt'?>


    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
